Harry Hoijer Collection 1930-1976 Mss.497.3.H68
American Philosophical Society
Harry Hoijer Collection, 1930-1976
Bulk, 1930-1934
Mss.497.3.H68
American Philosophical Society
4.0 Linear feet
A student of Edward Sapir's at the University of Chicago (PhD, 1931), Harry Hoijer began his career in linguistics with intensive fieldwork on the Coahuiltecan language, Tonkawa, though shortly thereafter he turned to an intensive study of Athapaskan, including several Apache languages, Navajo, Sarsi, and Galice. Employed as an instructor at the University of Chicago for several years, Hoijer moved to the new Department of Anthropology at UCLA in 1940, where he remained until his retirement. The Hoijer Collection contains textual materials representing comparative linguistic studies of Athapascan languages, including Carrier, Chipewyan, Galice, Navajo, Sarsi, and five Apache languages and dialects, (Chiricahua, Jicarilla, Mescalero, Lipan, and San Carlos). The collection also includes four audio recordings of Loucheux (Kutchin, Gwich'in), and copies of texts collected by Hoijer from colleagues Berard Haile, Diamond Jenness, David Mandelbaum, Chic Sandoval, and Edward Sapir.
Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976
Other Finding Aids note
The Hoijer Collection is also described in the online Daythal Kendall Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society.
Separated Materials note
The Loucheux recordings (Series IV) are stored with the Audiovisual Collections (Rec. 149).
Related Archival Materials note
Additional correspondence of Hoijer's is located in the papers of Franz Boas (B B61) and John Alden Mason (B M384).
Related material of Apache and other Athapaskan languages is index in the online Daythal Kendall Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired, 1973 (accn. no. 1976-1454ms).
Scope and Contents note
Dating primarily from the 1930s, the Hoijer Collection reflects the dedication to fieldwork that lay behind Harry Hoijer's extensive publications on Athapascan languages. The collection includes representative samples of his work in several Apache languages and dialects (Chiricahua, Mescalero, Jicarilla, and Lipan), Navajo, Galice, and Sarsi, as well as comparative data in several Athapascan languages.
The collection is composed of four series: (I) Correspondence, (II) Works by Harry Hoijer, (III) Works Collected by Harry Hoijer, and (IV) Recordings. The bulk of the collection consists of fieldnotes and typescripts of Hoijer's transcribed and translated texts from several Athapascan languages: Chiricahua, Jicarilla, Lipan Apache, Mescalero, and Navajo. The collection also includes samples of Hoijer's detailed linguistic notes on Carrier, Galice, Sarci, and comparative notes on Athapascan.
Hoijer's transcriptions of Navajo Songs and Night Chants (Series II) include extensive notes, with some drawings, on the conduct of the ceremony. Series III includes texts collected by Hoijer from his fellow researchers, including Berard Haile (Jicarilla), Diamond Jenness (Sarci), David Mandelbaum (San Carlos Apache), and Chic Sandoval (Navajo).
Hoijer's close association with Edward Sapir is documented at several different stages: the field notes on Navajo grammar (Kendall 4575) date to Hoijer's graduate years at Chicago; as Sapir's literary executor, Hoijer devoted several years to the publication, in 1974, of A Navajo Lexicon (see Kendall 4565 in the APS collection). Though limited, the correspondence (Series I) includes one letter from Edward Sapir.
Biographical/Historical note
Harry Hoijer was born to immigrant Swedish parents in Chicago in 1904. He studied mathematics and engineering at the University of Chicago (B.A. 1927) and only began his research into American Indian languages as a graduate student at the University of Chicago (M.A. 1929, Ph.D. 1931). He continued at Chicago as instructor in anthropology until 1940, when he was appointed Assistant Professor in the newly formed Department of Anthropology and Sociology at the University of California, Los Angeles. At Chicago, Hoijer was most influenced by Edward Sapir, with whom he shared a lifelong professional association.
At UCLA, Hoijer was instrumental in developing the Graduate Program in Linguistics, chairing the interdepartmental program from 1959 to 1963, when the Department of Linguistics was established. His own affiliation at UCLA remained with the Department of Anthropology. With Ralph L. Beals he co-authored An Introduction to Anthropology (1953; 4th ed., 1971).
Hoijer was a visiting professor in regular and summer sessions at several universities, and taught in nine of the summer linguistic institutes sponsored by the Linguistic Society of America. From 1950 until his retirement he chaired the Committee on Research in American Indian Languages, sponsored by the American Council of Learned Societies. He served as President of the American Anthropological Association in 1958 and President of the Linguistic Society of America in 1959. He was also a consultant to the UNESCO Commission on Language and Mentality.
Hoijer placed his scholarship at the service of the community. He introduced a statement for the defense in the Sleepy Lagoon murder trial, refuting the prosecution's contention that the defendants had inherited a blood lust from the Aztec ancestors. He also joined the fight against the abusive and infamous Loyalty Oath controversy at the University of California, and was subpoenaed by the California Committee on Un-American Activities.
His many publications reflect his dedication to both linguistics and anthropology. His doctoral fieldwork on the Coahuiltecan language, Tonkawa, in Oklahoma resulted in the publication of an important sketch in the Handbook of American Indian Languages (1933). With the later publication of Tonkawa Texts (1972), Hoijer created a lasting testimony to Tonkawa culture. His later studies were concentrated on the Athapascan languages of the American Southwest and the Pacific Coast. Like the inaugural work on Tonkawa, they were the result of extensive fieldwork.
In addition to his own publications, Hoijer inherited a corpus of materials from Edward Sapir, as well as the responsibility of acting as Sapir's literary executor. The Navajo Lexicon published in 1974, was Hoijer's last major work. Like Navajo Texts (1942), it was the product of a collaboration between Hoijer and Sapir. Hoijer also served in editorial capacities on the International Journal of American Linguistics and the American Anthropologist.
An extensive bibliography of Hoijer's publications was published by William Bright in IJAL 30 (1964):169-174; this is supplemented by select bibliographies in two necrological essays: by Victoria Fromkin, in Language 53 (1977):169-173, and by Ralph L. Beals, in the American Anthropologist 79 (1977):105-110.
Carrier language; Chiricahua Apache language; Ethnographic texts; Field notes.; Galice language; Indians of North America--Languages; Jicarilla language; Linguistic texts; Linguistics; Lipan Apache language; Mescalero language; Navajo language; San Carlos Apache language; Sarsi language; Slip files
- Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1976; 5 items
  - to Whitfield J. Bell (American Philosophical Society), September 30, 1976; Hoijer, Dorothy (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Describes some items in the donated collection, lists native informants, and gives details on the manner of place of recording some data.
  - List of five names, n.d.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    Possible suggested readers for a manuscript or suggested contacts on Sapir.
  - to Harry Hoijer, November 2, 1935; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Box 1)
    Comparative data on verb forms in Carrier, Lujan, Ts'ets'ant
  - Correspondence reagrding grant from American Philosophical Society, April 10-21, 1939; University of Chicago. (Box 1)
    Letters regarding the application of the balance from the APS grant from Yale to University of Chicago for use by Hoijer
    - to E. G. Conklin, April 10, 1939; Ostrander, H. J. (Box 1)
      Copy to Jean Sapir, acknolwedging letter of April 5, approving transfer of grant to Hoijer, with handwritten note by Jean Sapier, stating the balance was to be used to support Chic Sandoval's fieldwork on Navajo.
    - to H. J. Ostrander, April 14, 1939; Woodward, Frederick (Box 1)
      Acknowledging receipt of check for balance of grant.
    - to Harry Hoijer, April 21, 1939; Sandoval, Chic (Box 1)
      Agrees to take over Sapir's Navajo materials.
  - to Harry Hoijer, August 19, 1974; Unidentified correspondent (Box 1)
    Re: research on Sapir and the history of anthropology at the University of Chicago.
- Series II. Works by Hoijer (Box 1)
  - Carrier vowels and consonants, 4012 [fix]; AMs, 2p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    Charts of phonetic values of Carrier vowels and consonants.
  - Chiricahua texts, fieldnotes, 1930, 1934; 4176; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    Chiricahua texts with interlinear English glosses and English translations [H.H.'s fieldnotes while with the Univ. of Chicago Dept of Anthropology]. Inside cover of first notebook reads "Crook-Neck--Lipan speaking. About 60 yrs.--about mile from Sam's place". Informant: Sam Kenoi.
    Texts are annotated for publication; many titles are corrected in the translation; some titles are numbered as well.
    - Chiricahua texts, fieldnotes #1, 1930; 1 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
      Contents:
      Old Times (June 17, 1930) (pp. 1-4)
      Coyote and the White Man (June 18, 1930) (pp. 4v-14)
      Coyote and the Rock Rabbit 9 (or, The Rabbit Stuffed with Rocks) (June 18, 1930) (pp. 14v-15) no. 12
      Coyote and the Rolling Rock (June 19, 1930) (pp. 15v-19) no. 14
      Coyote Misses Rock Rabbit (n.d.) (pp. 19v-21) no. 13
      Coyote and the Stink Bug (n.d.) (pp. 21v-25) no. 15
      Coyote and the Lizard (June 21, 1930) (pp. 25v-33) no. 16
      Coyote Dances with the Prairie Dogs (June 25, 1930) (pp. 33v-49) no. 17
      Coyote Marries His Own Daughter (pp. 49v-60), no. 18 [cont'd in Notebook 2]
    - Chiricahua texts, fieldnotes #2, 1930, 1934; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
      Coyote marries His Own Daughter (pp. 1-5) no. 18 [continued from Notebook 1]
      The Birth of Tóhágì._tcìnέ_ (pp. 6v-16) no. 1
      The Killing of the Dragon (pp. 16v-38) no. 2
      The Killing of the Bull (pp. 38v-44) no. 3
      The Killing of the Eagle (pp. 44v-53) no. 4
      The Killing of the Prairie Dogs (pp. 53v-59) no. 5 [continues in Notebook 3]
    - Chiricahua texts, fieldnotes #3, 1930, 1934; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
      Prairie Dogs, etc. (p. 1), no. 5 [continued from Notebook 2]
      The Creation (pp. 1v-8) no. 6
      The Gambling Game for Night and Day (pp. 8v-18) no. 7
      Coyote Obtains Fire (pp. 18v-24) no. 10
      The Quarrel between the Thunder and the Wind (pp. 24v-29) no. 8
      The Sun (p. 30) no. 9
      Old Apache Customs (pp. 31-57) no. 39
      The First Gáhέ Dance (pp. 57v-61) no. 19 [continues in Notebook 4]
    - Chiricahua texts, fieldnotes #4, 1930, 1934; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
      The First Gáhέ Dance (pp. 1-22) no. 19 [continued from Notebook 3]
      The Visit of the Mountain Spirits (pp. 22v-37) no. 20
    - Chiricahua texts, fieldnotes #5, 1930, 1934; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
      [page-numbering stops at 30; supplied numbers are in brackets]
      The Foolish People and the Missing Pack (March 20, 1934) (pp. 1-5) no. 24
      The Foolish People Imitate the Crow (March 20, 1934) (pp. 5v-7) no. 25
      The Apache and the Commanche [sic] (March 20, 1934) (pp. 7v-9) no. 32
      The Foolish People and the Horse (March 20, 1934) (pp. 9v-12) no. 26
      The Fake Medicine Man (March 20, 1934) (pp. 12v-17) no. 33
      The Foolish People and the White Man (March 20, 1934) (p. 17v-19) no. 22
      The Foolish People Acquire Copper (March 20, 1934) (pp. 19v-22) no. 28
      The Foolish People Go to War (March 20, 1934) (pp. 23-24) no. 29
      The Foolish People Run Away (March 20, 1934) (pp. 24v-26) no. 30
      The Woman Shaman (March 20, 1934) (pp. 26v-29) no. 34
      A Visit to the Mountain Spirits (March 23, 1934) 29v-[p. 35] no. 22
      The Mountain People and the Cripples (March 23, 1934) [pp. 35v-37] no. 23
      The Woman Who Had Horse Power (March 23, 1934) [pp. 37v-40] no. 35
      A Girl is Lost (March 23, 1934) [pp. 40v-42] no. 36
      The Girl and the Water Spirit (March 23, 1934) [pp. 42v-45] no. 37
      Stories of the Foolish People (March 23, 1934) [pp. 45v-48] no. 31
      The Old Woman's Grandson [pp. 48v-60] no. 38 [indications that the legend is continued in another notebook; see notes to Box 6]
  - Chiricahua and Mescalero fieldnotes, 1934; 4175; 1 notebook; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    One notebook, entitled "Close of Duncan's Long Apache Texts Vol. VII, Mescalero", containing Mescalero texts in phonemic transcription, with interlinear English glosses, English translation and additional notes on facing page. According to Kendall, this is last of the series begun in 4176 [= Box 5].
    [continuation of a story]
    A Hunting Trip (18 pp) no. 9
    Coyote and Dove (3 pp) no. 6
    Coyote Marries his Daughter (6 pp) [text crossed out] no. 7
  - Chiricahua texts in translation, n.d.; 4174; 23p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    Typescript. English translations only [not proofread]; some tales in multiple copies. Informant and translator; Sam Kenoi.
    Coyote and the White Man (3 pp.)
    Coyote and the Rabbit Stuffed with Rocks (1 p.)
    Coyote and the Rolling Rock (1 p.)
    Coyote Misses Real Rabbit (1 p.)
    Coyote Marries his own Daughter (2 pp.)
    The Foolish People and the Missing Pack (7 pp., several versions)
    The Foolish People Imitate the Crow (2 pp.)
    The Apache and the Comanche (2 pp.)
    The Foolish People and the Horse (2 pp.)
    The False Medicine Man (2 pp.)
  - Comparative Athapascan [lexical], 4113; ca.300 slips; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Othertype Slipfile 1)
    5x7 handwritten slips, alphabetically arranged, according to the English gloss. Comparative lexical data from Sarsi, Chipewyan, and Navajo.
  - Comparative Athapascan Affixes, n.d.; 4112; 27p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    Charts of comparative data taken from 33 languages and dialects. Athapascan data, with English glosses, e.g., Sarsi sínì, Chip. sì, Nav. šì, Engl. 'I am'
  - Galice Record, n.d.; 4259; 16p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    Handwritten on looseleaf, listing lexical items in phonemic transcription, with English glosses, e.g., dalbai. Lexicon includes nouns, pronouns, prepositions, adverbs, adjectives, as well as inflected forms of nouns ('my wife, your wife, his wife') and phrases (e.g., 'I shall see it', 'what are you doing?'). According to Kendall, nouns and verbs with person markers, but no complete paradigms..
  - Jicarilla Texts, Fieldnotes, n.d.; 4433; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
    5 notebooks of Jicarilla texts in phonemic transcription, with interlinear English glosses. The notebooks, labeled 1 to 5, are paginated separately (some tales carry over). Informants: Cevero Caramillo and Alasco Tiznada. According to Kendall, texts in 4430 and 4433 are the same.
    - Jicarilla Texts, Fieldnotes, Notebook 1 ("Coyote stories"), n.d.; 1 notebook; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
      [untitled] (pp. 1v-2)
      Coyote and Lizard (10-17-34) (pp. 2v-4) no. 2
      Coyote Eats a Meadow Mouse (10-18-34) (pp. 5-11) no. 3
      [untitled] (10-18-34) (pp. 13-16)
      Coyote and Elk (10-18-34) (pp. 16v-22) no. 5
      The Gambling Game for Day [n.d.] (pp. 22v-29) no. 6
      The Man Who Liked to Gamble (pp. 30-60) no. 7 [continues in notebook 2]
    - Jicarilla Texts, Fieldnotes, Notebook 2 ("Alasco Tiznada, pp.1-60"), n.d.; 1 notebook; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
      [The Man Who Liked to Gamble; continued from notebook 1] [n.d.] (pp. 1-11)
      The Woman who Became a Deer [n.d.] (pp. 11v-60)
    - Jicarilla Texts, Fieldnotes, Notebook 3 ("Alasco Tiznada, interptered by Cevero Caramillo"), n.d.; 1 notebook; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)
      Entries untitled.
    - Jicarilla Texts, Fieldnotes, Notebook 4 ("Alasco Tiznada, interptered by Cevero Caramillo"), n.d.; 1 notebook; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 2)
    - Jicarilla Texts, Fieldnotes, Notebook 5 ("Alasco Tiznada, interptered by Cevero Caramillo"), n.d.; 1 notebook; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 2)
  - Jicarilla Texts 1, n.d.; 4430; 350p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 2)
    Typed mss of ten texts: Coyote stories told by Cevero Caramillo; remaining texts by Alasco Tiznada, with the help of Cevero Caramillo. Each text contains four parts: Jicarilla text in phonemic transcription, English gloss (or literal translation), English translation, second English gloss.
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 1a)
      The Translation: Preface (1 p)
      Texts:
      1. The Greedy Coyote (4 pp)
      2. Coyote and Lizard (4 pp)
      3. Coyote Eats a Meadow Mouse (10 pp)
      4. Coyote and Buffalo (8 pp)
      5. Coyote and Elk (6 pp)
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 1b)
      6. The Gambling Game for Day (10 pp)
      7. The Man Who Liked to Gamble (54 pp)
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 1c)
      8. The Woman Who Became a Deer (26 pp)
      9. The Trip to the Plains for Buffalo (21 pp)
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 1)
      10. The Abandoned Children (193 pp total), part 1
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 1e)
      10. The Abandoned Children, part 2
  - Jicarilla Texts 2, n.d.; 4432; ca.250p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 2)
    Phonemic transcription and translation of texsts 1-10 (see Jicarilla texts 1).
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 2a)
      Contents (phonemic transcriptions):
      1. The Greedy Coyote
      2. Coyote and Lizard
      3. Coyote Eats a Meadow Mouse
      4. Coyote and Buffalo
      5. Coyote and Elk
      6. The Gambling Game for Day
      7. The Man Who Liked to Gamble
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 2b)
      8. The Woman Who Became a Deer
      9. The Trip to the Plains for Buffalo
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 2c)
      10. The Abandoned Children
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 2)
      Contents (translation):
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 2e)
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 2)
    - Jicarilla Texts 1, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 2g)
  - Jicarilla Texts 3 [handwritten], 4432; 10 folders; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 2)
    Handwritten pages on looseleaf, containing Jicarilla texts of ten tales, in phonemic transcription, with interlinear English glosses. Approx. 250 pp.
    Same stories as Jicarilla texts 1 and 2.
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 3a)
      Informant: Cevero Caramillo
      The Greedy Coyote (2 pp. [missing p. 1]), no. 1
      Coyote and Lizard (2 pp.), no. 2
      Coyote Eats a Meadow Mouse (4 pp.), no. 3
      Coyote and Buffalo (3 pp.), no. 4
      Coyote and Elk (3 pp.), no. 5
      Informant: Alasco Tiznada
      The Gambling Game for Day (4 pp. [p. 1 includes taped note to add to l. 7]), no. 6
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 3b)
      Informant: Alasco Tiznada: The Man Who Liked to Gamble (31 pp. [only Jicarilla text, no English]), no. 7
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 3c)
      Informant: Alasco Tiznada: The Man Who Liked to Gamble (26 pp. [second version: Jicarilla and English])
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 3)
      [Informant not specified]: The Woman Who Became a Deer (22 pp.), no. 8
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Folder 3e)
      [Informant not specified]: The Trip to the Plains for Buffalo (17 pp.), no. 9
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      [Informant not specified]: The Abandoned Children (pp. 1-33), no. 10
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3g)
      [continues 3f]: The Abandoned Children (pp. 34-66
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3h)
      [continues 3g]: The Abandoned Children (pp. 67-99)
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3i)
      [continues 3h]: The Abandoned Children (pp. 100-132)
    - Jicarilla Texts 3, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3j)
      [continues 3i]: The Abandoned Children (pp. 133-166 [conclusion])
  - Lipan Apache Fieldnotes, Late 1930s; 4474; 1 notebook; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
    Unpaginated [supplied page numbers are given in brackets]. Texts in Lipan Apache in phonemic transcription, with interlinear English glosses, and notes to the texts on facing pages. N.B. This notebook is rather frail.
    At School. Informant: Lisandro Mendez [pp. 4-8]
    Further Schooling. Informant: L[isandro] M[endez] [pp. 8v-10]
    Text 4 [no title]. Informant: Augustina Zuazua. [pp. 10v-59]
  - Lipan Texts, n.d.; 4475; 8p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
    Typed texts in phonemic transcription, with English translations on separate pages. Informant: Lisandro Mendez.
    Deer and Coyote (2 pp.)
    At School (4 pp.)
    Further Schooling (2 pp.)
  - Lipan: "The History and Customs of the Lipan", 1975; 4473; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
    Offprint of an article published by Harry Hoijer in the journal Linguistics 161 (1975): 5-38. Also contains typed draft. This is the final version of the text contained in Kendall 4474.
  - Mescalero fieldnotes, n.d.; 4503, 4504; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
    Mescalero texts in phonemic transcription, with interlinear English glosses, and notes to the texts on facing pages. Not fully paginated [supplied page numbers are given in brackets].
    - Mescalero fieldnotes, notebook #1 ("Apache texts"), n.d.; 4503; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
      Apache Prayer. Informant: Horace Torres [with symbols] (pp. 1-[7])
      Bird Song. Informant: Arnold K. [pp. 7v-8]
      Squirrel Song [pp. 8v-9]
      Turkey Song [pp. 9v-10]
      War Song. Informant: Arnold K.[pp. 10v-11]
      War Dance Song. Warm Springs Chiri [p. 11v]
      Gá.hé Song. Informant: Leon Pariko [p. 12]
      [no title][pp. 13-14]
      Prayer. Informant: Sam Chino [pp. 15-21]
      Songs [pp. 21v-23]
      Moccasin Songs. Informant: Sam Chino [pp. 24-26]
      Mescalero 3 Text. Informant: John Shanta [pp. 27-29]
    - Mescalero fieldnotes, notebook #2, n.d.; 4503; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
      Mescalero Creation Myth. Informant: Sam Chino (pp. 1-10)
      Mescalero Creation. Informant: Sam Chino (pp. 11-27)
      Fire Story (pp. 28-34)
      The Sun Wind Thunder Rain etc. Have a Quarrel (pp. 33-38)
      Coyote (pp. 39-44)
      Coyote (pp. 45-60)
    - Mescalero fieldnotes, notebook #3 ("Horace Torres, Coyote, Origin, Texts: Mescalero"), n.d.; 4503; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
      [Only last twenty pages are numbered, beginning with p. 1]
      [no titles] [pp. 1-40]
      The Killing of the Monsters [41-60]
    - Mescalero fieldnotes, notebook 4 ("Mescalero Apache Texts"), 1934; 4504; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
      Coyote and the Blue Bunting (April 2, 1934) (pp. 1-5), no. 1
      Coyote and Owl (April 2, 1934) (pp. 6-16), no. 2
      Coyote and Beaver (April 3, 1934) (pp. 17-35), no. 3
      Coyote and Turtle (pp. 36-44), no. 4 [continues in notebook 5]
    - Mescalero Apache Texts, notebook 5, 1934; 4504; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
      Coyote and Turtle [continued from Notebook 1] (April 3, 1934) (pp. 1-5)